A Finding Aid to the Daniel Varney Thompson Papers, 1848-1979, bulk 1923-1979, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Daniel Varney Thompson papers
1848-1979
bulk 1923-1979
Archives of American Art
Thompson, Daniel V. (Daniel Varney), 1902-1980
AAA.thomdani
Archival Resource Key
10.1 Linear feet
The papers of art conservator and historian, engineer, and professor Daniel Varney Thompson (1902-1980) are dated 1848-1979, with the bulk of the material dated 1923-1979. The collection measures 10.1 linear feet and consists of biographical material, correspondence, subject files, writings, artwork, printed material, and photographs.
Provenance
The Daniel Varney Thompson papers were donated to the Archives of American Art in increments between 1974-1981 by Mr. Thompson and his estate.
Related Material
Also found in the Archives of American Art are oral history interviews conducted with Daniel V. Thompson by Robert Brown, September 25, 1974-November 2, 1976. There are also three letters from Thompson to his sister-in-law Edith Simonds Moore.
Alternative Forms Available
A portion of the collection is available on 35 mm microfilm reel 888 at the Archives of American Art offices and through interlibrary loan. Researchers should note that the arrangement of the material described in the container inventory does not reflect the arrangement of the collection on microfilm.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Biographical Note
Daniel Varney Thompson (1902-1980) was an art conservator and historian, professor, engineer, and writer. A noted authority on medieval painting, Varney lived and worked primarily in the Boston area and London.
Daniel Varney Thompson was born in New Jersey in 1902. He was the son of Grace Randall Thompson and Daniel Varney Thompson, Sr., a classics teacher at the Lawrenceville School and later headmaster of Boston Latin School. American composer Randall Thompson was his older brother. Following family tradition, Thompson attended Harvard, earning the A.B. in 1922 and A.M. in 1926, focusing his attention on fine arts, physical chemistry, and literature. Daniel V. Thompson stopped using the designation Jr. after his father's death in 1932.
Between 1922 and 1925 Thompson was employed in the Fogg Museum's laboratory devoted to analyzing art materials for the purposes of detecting forgeries, preserving works of art, and devising methods to aid working artists. During this period, Thompson went to Italy as a Sheldon Fellow in Fine Arts, to learn medieval fresco painting techniques from Edward W. Forbes, Director of the Fogg Museum. He also had an opportunity to study medieval and Renaissance painting techniques with Inicio Federico Joni, and while in Italy began life-long friendships with the Forbes family and Bernard Berenson. Thompson served as a technical advisor to the 1924-1925 Second Harvard China Expedition; he traveled to China by way of India, where he studied wall paintings in caves at Ajanta and Elura and researched newly discovered scrolls.
Daniel Varney Thompson was on the faculty of Yale from 1926-1933, where he taught art history, and tempera painting courses, and laid the foundation for the Department of Fine Arts when Yale became a university in 1932. During his time at Yale, Thompson married Cecile [Cecily] de Luze Simonds.
When The American Council of Learned Societies awarded Thompson a research fellowship for the academic year 1933/34, he returned to Europe and surveyed major libraries for materials concerning the history of technology of the arts. Thompson was then invited to be Professor of the History of Technology at the University of London. He was on the faculty from 1934-1946, and also served as research and technical advisor, developing a laboratory at the Courtauld Institute for analysis of art materials.
During World War II, the Courtauld's laboratory - which had facilities for emission, absorption, and x-ray spectrography - was offered to the Ministry of Aircraft Production. To avoid compromising the University's tax-free status, Thompson formed and served as managing director of Daniel Varney Limited, a private company which leased the premises and equipment. From 1940 to 1945, the company was operated in the name of the Courtauld Institute, employing 200 people in tool making, gauge making, fine mechanisms, and development and production of optics instruments. After the war, Daniel Varney Limited shifted its interests to high vacuum diffusion pumps, gas manipulation, and glassblowing.
Upon returning to the United States in 1947, Thompson settled in the Boston area, becoming a technical consultant. He worked on projects for E-Z Mills, Inc., Sylvania Eloctronics, Comstock & Wescott, Inc., and other corporations. He was chief engineer of Jarrell-Ash Co., 1953-1955, redesigning optical instruments, spectrography, and schlieren systems. Between 1955 and 1957, Thompson served as Vice President of Swett & Sibley, involved with the design and development of optical instruments, scanning spectrometers, and densistometers. He then moved to Avco Corporation, where for the next decade he was a Senior Staff Consultant working on optical design in rocket instrumentation. Thompson retired from his engineering career in 1967.
Daniel V. Thompson wrote and published extensively. Art-related writings include translations and a monograph published by Yale University Press, and numerous articles and reviews. Translations are: Cennino Cennini's Il Libro dell'Arte (3 volumes: Text of Il Libro dell'Arte, 1932; The Craftsman's Handbook, 1933; and The Practice of Tempera Painting, 1936), and An Anonymous Fourteenth Century Treatise ( De arte illuminadi) (with his student George Heard Hamilton), 1936. A monograph, The Materials and Techniques of Medieval Painting (foreword by Bernard Berenson) appeared in 1936.
Most of Thompson's scientific and technical writings are unpublished and relate to projects for which he served as a consulting engineer.
Soon after retiring, Thompson began a new career that he continued for the remainder of his life. A serious cook and long-time gardener, he began writing about these topics, producing weekly columns that were published by newspapers from Maine to Chicago and contributing articles to Gourmet, Horticulture, and similar periodicals. Thompson also lectured to garden clubs and judged garden and flower competitions.
Daniel Varney Thompson died on January 4, 1980, following an automobile accident in Malaga, Spain.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of art conservator and historian, professor, engineer, and writer Daniel Varney Thompson (1902-1980) are dated 1848-1979, with the bulk of the material dated 1923-1979. The collection measures 10.1 linear feet and consists of biographical material, correspondence, subject files, writings, artwork, printed material, and photographs.
Biographical information includes certificates and diplomas, passports, and wills. Correspondence documents Daniel Varney Thompson's personal and professional life. Personal correspondence centers heavily on family members including his brother, the composer Randall Thompson. Professional correspondence concerns Thompson's academic career, research, writing, and work as a technical consultant and engineer. Among the correspondents are colleagues from Harvard, Yale, the Courtauld Institute, publishers, and academic and technical journals, in addition to corporate clients.
Subject files are comprised of varying correspondence, printed matter, photographs, notes and writings relating to Thompson's areas of interest. Personal and professional subject files include many relating to his research interests and engineering consulting projects. Of particular interest are numerous letters from Bernard Berenson. There is also correspondence with Belle da Costa Greene, as well as files concerning the Kermes beetle (a source of crimson dyes in the middle ages). Food and gardening subject files reflect Thompson's career as a writer and columnist on these subjects.
Writings consist mainly of manuscripts, drafts, research and miscellaneous notes; also included are diaries, poems, miscellaneous items, and a music score. Daniel Varney Thompson's personal and professional writings include two diaries, poems, and student writings. Most of his extant writings are on art-related topics, science and technology. Among the notes is an index to medieval manuscripts on craftsmanship in major European libraries was compiled by Thompson in 1935. His work on the subject remains unpublished and his notes are extremely valuable since some of the materials noted were lost in World War II. Scientific and technical notebooks, along with various wirings and reports, document projects undertaken as a technical consultant and engineer. The food and gardening writings are extensive and consist of manuscripts and notes for articles and columns, and for a book-length compilation of these writings. Among the writings by other authors are diaries of his mother and wife, and a music score by his brother, Randall Thompson.
Artwork by Daniel Varney Thompson, Mary Sargent McKean, and Henry Winslow consists of drawings, prints, watercolors, a sketchbook, and an oil painting. Printed material includes articles and book reviews by Daniel Varney Thompson, and items about or mentioning him and his family. Also found are articles and books about art, history, medieval studies, science and technology, and food and gardening topics.
Photographs are of artwork, people, places and miscellaneous subjects. Images of people are mainly Thompson and family members.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 7 series.
Missing Title
Series 1: Biographical Information, 1848-1970s (Box 1, OV 11-12; 0.3 linear ft.)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1914-1979 (Boxes 1-3; 2.0 linear ft.)
Series 3: Subject Files, 1925-1979 (Boxes 3-6; 3.0 linear ft.)
Series 4: Writings, 1907-1970s (Boxes 6-9; 2.85 linear ft.)
Series 5: Artwork, 1923-1934 (Box 9, OV 13; 5 folders)
Series 6: Printed Material, 1917-1979 (Box 9; 0.75 linear ft.)
Series 7: Photographs, circa 1900-1972 (Box 10; 0.4 linear ft.)
Notebooks; Diaries; Sketchbooks; Drawings; Food; Watercolors; Gardening; Photographs; Engineers -- United States; Poetry; Authors -- Massachusetts; Musical scores; Conservators; Art historians; Prints; Oil paintings; Kermes (Insect); Manuscripts; Berenson, Bernard, 1865-1959; Greene, Belle da Costa, 1883-1950; Courtauld Institute of Art -- Faculty; McKean, Mary Sargeant; Winslow, Henry, b. 1874; Thompson, Randall, 1899-1984
- Biographical Information, 1848-1970s; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; (Box 1, OV 11-12; 0.3 linear ft.)
  Scope and Contents note
  Biographical information includes certificates and diplomas, passports, and wills. The item pre-dating Thompson's birth is a family document: the marriage certificate of Samuel Cogswell and Sarah Williams.
  Other information about the Thompson family is included in Thompson's diaries and those of his mother and wife, found among the writings (Series 4). Some printed material (Series 6) concerns the career of his brother, composer Randall Thompson, and other items mention his wife.
  Arrangement note
  Biographical information is arranged by record type and chronologically within folders.
  - Awards, 1917-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Biographical Notes, 1950s-1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Certificate (Registered Professional Engineer), 1970; Archival Resource Key; (see also OV 11) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Diploma, Archival Resource Key; (see OV 11) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Driver's License, 1933-1946; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Employment Applications and Recommendation, 1951-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Family Document, Marriage Certificate, 1848; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Passports, Archival Resource Key (Box 1)
    - Cecile deLuze Simonds Thompson, 1920-1941; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Daniel Varney Thompson, 1920-1944; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - John Ireland Thompson, 1937; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Selective Service Registration, 1943-1945; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Wills and Cemetery Deed, 1967, 1970; Archival Resource Key; (see also: OV 12) (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Certificate (Registered Professional Engineer) and Diploma (Harvard University), 1926, 1956; Archival Resource Key (Box OV 11)
  - Blueprint of Thompson Family Headstone, 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box OV 12)
- Correspondence, 1914-1979; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; (Boxes 1-3; 2.0 linear ft.)
  Correspondence documents Daniel Varney Thompson's personal and professional life. Mr. Thompson's brief notes about major correspondents immediately pecede the correspondence. Personal correspondence with friends and family includes many letters exchanged with his wife during their courtship and, later, when absent from home. Among the other family correspondence are a small number of letters from his parents, children, and brother, the composer Randall Thompson. Professional correspondence documents Thompson's academic career, research, and writing, and his later work as a technical consultant and engineer.
  Correspondence concerning Thompson's food and garden writing career and additional personal and professional correspondence is scattered among the Subject Files (Series 3).
  Correspondence is arranged in chronological order.
  - Notes on Correspondents by Daniel V. Thompson, circa 1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1914-1938; Archival Resource Key; (23 folders) (Box 1, Folder 14-36)
  - Correspondence, 1939-1973; Archival Resource Key; (22 folders) (Box 2, Folder 1-22)
  - Correspondence, 1974-1979; Archival Resource Key; (3 folders) (Box 3, Folder 1-3)
  - Correspondence, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 3)
    - January - December, Archival Resource Key; (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 4-5)
    - Sunday - Saturday, Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Clark, Katharine B. - York, Lewis E., Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Unidentified; Illegible, Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Subject Files, 1925-1979; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; (Boxes 3-6; 3.0 linear ft.)
  Subject files contain varying combinations of correspondence, printed material, photographs, notes and writings relating to Thompson's areas of interest.
  The series is arranged into 2 subseries:
  3.1: Personal and Professional, 1925-1979
  3.2: Food and Gardening, 1966-1974
  - Personal and Professional, 1925-1979; 3.1; Archival Resource Key
    Personal and professional subject files include many relating to engineering consulting projects and research interests. Of particular interest are the files on Bernard Berenson consisting of many letters to Thompson dated 1933-1957 and letters from Nicky Mariano, 1959-1966, and Creighton Giilbert, 1968. All of these items appear on microfilm reel 888. Also of note are a file titled Belle da Costa Greene concerning background information and the circumstances surrounding the death of her adopted son. Extensive correspondence, notes, photographs, and research materials (much photocopied) document Thompson's interest in Kermes beetles, the source of crimson dyes in the Middle Ages.
    - Avco Corporation, 1959-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Berenson, Bernard, 1933-1935; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Berenson, Bernard, 1936-1939; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Berenson, Bernard, 1945-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Berenson, Bernard, 1939-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - China Expedition, Harvard University, 1925; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Consulting Projects, Archival Resource Key (Box 3)
      - Mechanical/Optical Instrument System, 1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 15)
      - Miscellaneous, 1949-1957, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 16)
      - Schlieren-Shadowgraph System, 1955-1956; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 17)
      - Tension Frame TF2, 1949; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 18)
      - Wavemeter G79, 1942; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 19)
      - Wyckoff Hydrogen Discharge Tube, 1953; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Daniel Varney, Ltd., 1945-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Dover Publications, Inc., 1955-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Greene, Belle da Costa, 1943-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Hindu Paintings at Elloru, 1925-1933; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Jarrell-Ash Company, 1952-1955, undated; Archival Resource Key; (5 folders) (Box 3, Folder 25-29)
    - Jones, R. V., 1951-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Kermes Beetles(see also: "Memorial" of the Kermes Group Luncheon), Archival Resource Key (Box 3)
      - Correspondence and Notes, 1978-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 31)
      - Photographs, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 32)
      - Research Material [including photocopies of material dated 1733], 1984, undated; Archival Resource Key; (3 folders) (Box 3, Folder 33-35)
    - Leases and Mortgage, 1932-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Lucas, Sam, 1951-1974, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Mariano, Nicky (see: Berenson, Bernard), Archival Resource Key (Box 4)
    - "Memorial" of the Kermés Group Luncheon, 1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Sylvania Electric Products, Inc., 1951; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - University of Glasgow, 1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Food and Gardening, 1966-1974; 3.2; Archival Resource Key
    Food and gardening subject files document Thompson's career as a writer and columnist on these subjects. Included are extensive files of correspondence with readers, as well as editorial correspondence.
    - Agents, 1970-1973, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - B. P. Singer Features, 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Backer, Sally ("Sally's Own Cookbook"), 1968-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Banks, Emily A., 1969-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Book Reviews, 1966-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Boyden, Sarah, 1967-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Chicago Sun-Times, 1968-1973 (see also: Readers -; Archival Resource Key; (2 folders) (Box 4, Folder 12-13)
    - Dun and Lapham Agents for Writers, 1971-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Editor and Publisher, 1967-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Family Circle, 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Flower and Garden Magazine (see also: Readers - Flower and Garden Magazine), 1969-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - "Food and Garden Gossip" (column), 1970-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - "Foodmanship" (column), 1969-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Francatelli, Charles Elme (see: "Queen Victoria's Chef"), Archival Resource Key (Box 4)
    - Gloxinia-Gesneriad Society, 1968-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Gourmet (see also: Readers - Gourmet), 1966-1974, undated; Archival Resource Key; (6 folders) (Box 4, Folder 21-26)
    - Greaves, Harry, 1970-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Hearthside Press, 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Horticulture, 1968-1972, undated; Archival Resource Key; (2 folders) (Box 4, Folder 29-30)
    - Hubley, Ben, 1968-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Kennedy Special Common Crackers, 1967-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Krech, Inez, 1971-1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Melanson, Harold R., 1968-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - Morton, Miriam L., 1971-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - North Shore Magazine/Essex County Newspapers, Inc. (see also: Readers - North Shore Magazine), 1966-1973; Archival Resource Key; (5 folders) (Box 5, Folder 1-5)
    - "Pleasures of Food and Garden" (column), 1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Possible Clients, 1968-1973, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Press (Binghamton, N.Y.) (see also: Readers - Press (Binghamton, N.Y.), 1969-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Press Herald-Evening Express (Portland, Maine) (see also: Readers - Press Herald-Evening Express, 1968-1973; Archival Resource Key; (5 folders) (Box 5, Folder 9-13)
    - "Queen Victoria's Chef" ( The Modern Cook by Charles Elme Francatelli), 1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence With Readers, Archival Resource Key (Box 5)
      - Chicago Sun-Times, 1969-1972; Archival Resource Key; (3 folders) (Box 5, Folder 15-17)
      - Flower and Garden Magazine, 1970-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 18)
      - Gourmet, 1969-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 19)
      - Miscellaneous, 1968-1974, undated; Archival Resource Key; (4 folders) (Box 5, Folder 20-23)
      - North Shore Magazine, 1968-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 24)
      - Press, Binghamton, N.Y., 1969-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 25)
      - Press Herald-Evening Express (Portland, Me.), 1968-1972; Archival Resource Key; (5 folders) (Box 5, Folder 26-30)
      - Worcester Telegram (Worcester, Mass.), 1968-1870; Archival Resource Key; (3 folders) (Box 5, Folder 31-33)
    - Recipes, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Risley, Dorothy, 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Saylor, William R., 1969-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Seeds and Supplies, 1967-1972; Archival Resource Key; (2 folders) (Box 6, Folder 4-5)
    - Speaking Engagements, 1968-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Wilder, Isabel, 1966-1973; Archival Resource Key; (2 folders) (Box 6, Folder 7-8)
    - Wines Internationale, 1969-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Worcester Telegram (Worcester, Mass.) (see also: Readers - Worcester Telegram), 1967-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Yankee, 1969-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Writings, 1907-1970s; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; (Boxes 6-9; 2.85 linear ft.)
  Writings consist mainly of manuscripts, drafts, research and miscellaneous notes; also included are diaries, poems, miscellaneous items, and a music score. Additional writings by Thompson and other authors are found among the subject files (Series 3).
  The series is arranged as 3 subseries:
  4.1: By Daniel Varney Thompson - Personal and Professional, 1921-1966
  4.2: By Daniel Varney Thompson - Food and Garden, 1960s-1970s
  4.3: By Other Authors, 1907-1967
  - By Daniel Varney Thompson - Personal and Professional, 1921-1966; 4.1; Archival Resource Key
    The personal and professional writings of Daniel Varney Thompson are on art-related topics, science and technology. An index to medieval manuscripts on craftsmanship in major European libraries was compiled by Thompson in 1935 (2 card files). His work on the subject remains unpublished and his notes are extremely valuable since some of the materials noted were lost in World War II. In addition, there are notes and research materials relating to Thompson's translation work. His scientific and technical notebooks (10 vols.) and various writings and reports document projects undertaken as a technical consultant and engineer from the late 1930s through 1960s. Also extant are two diaries, poems, and student writings.